All right, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is י"ד. yud-daled.
We pick up where we're a bit ahead. We pick up towards
the bottom of י"ד עמוד א', yud-daled amud aleph, האומר לאשתו הרי
את עלי כאמא. ha-omer le-ishto harei at alai ke-ima. So we had
just dealt with the משנה mishnah that laid out the important principle
that if somebody wants to use the language of a נדר, neder,
that this should be like חזיר, chazir, like שקצים ורמשים, shekatzim u-remasim,
even like עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, that is not a נדר neder
because a נדר neder has to use as the paradigm, as the
model, דבר הנדור, davar ha-nadur, something that becomes forbidden as a result
of the person's verbal
assignment of status, creating the status of the object, which is not
true no matter how forbidden these other things are. They're forbidden because
the תורה Torah made them forbidden. So I wanted to actually mention
two points about this to clarify or go back to something we
discussed yesterday. First of all, we was grappling with the issue about
why חלה challah and תרומה terumah is not considered a דבר הנדור
davar ha-nadur in the משנה, mishnah, because that certainly is a status
that's created through a person's speech.
And the ר"ן Ran says, thank you, that some have because it's
not fully forbidden that it shows that it's some type
of a prohibition the תורה Torah put on it and not resulting
of the status of תרומה terumah that the person created, which I
really do not understand. That's the implications of the status of תרומה
terumah the same way when somebody sanctifies an animal for a קרבן,
korban, the implications are that it's fully אסור. assur. And also, so
to me it seems that it's just some assumption, not articulated assumption,
that the model again, the paradigm has to be something that is
fully forbidden although the reality is that a person can make a
נדר neder that's not forbidden in all respects, only for eating, not
for הנאה, hana'ah, only for certain use, not for another use, and
can make something forbidden to some people and not to all people.
Still the sort of the paradigm has to be something that is
forbidden across the board and to all people. Lynn suggested another interesting
approach which was that since טבל tevel is already forbidden, then when
a person makes something תרומה terumah or חלה, challah, the dough or
the grain was already אסור assur by טבל. tevel. So the person
is not actually making it forbidden, they're actually in a way, I
mean it remains forbidden, maybe forbidden from a different perspective. Actually, there's
an interesting discussion about טבל tevel that maybe the whole status of
the grain being טבל tevel is a result of the fact that
there is potential תרומה terumah that is present in the grain. So
maybe that's the person is not really fully instilling that status. I
did check. I thought an interesting test case for that would be
ביכורים bikkurim because ביכורים bikkurim is also permissible to כהנים kohanim and
not to non-כהנים, kohanim, but ביכורים bikkurim doesn't, not taking of ביכורים
bikkurim doesn't make something טבל. tevel. In all of my research, which
is with my, which is my good friend Rabbi Bar-Ilan,
I was not able to find any discussion of saying something should
be כביכורים ke-bikkurim by נדרים, nedarim, which I think would be a
real, yeah, I was really shocked because I thought I had remembered
but not in the גמרא Gemara and not in the רמב"ם. Rambam.
I did however see looking in the רמב"ם, Rambam, the רמב"ם Rambam
has a different answer to this question and which is interesting conceptually
because the רמב"ם Rambam actually says דבר הנדור davar ha-nadur does not
just mean what we've been discussing, which is a object that you
have created its forbidden status through your act of speech, but the
רמב"ם Rambam actually hearkens back to the original biblical idea of נדר,
neder, which is to freely offer something to God. And the רמב"ם
Rambam says that the דבר הנדור davar ha-nadur has to be a
type of a thing that not only is created through your speech
offering but through a free offering that a person makes to God.
So the obvious question the רמב"ם Rambam deals with is and how
can you say this could be like a חטאת, chattat, this could
be like an אשם, asham, that comes through an obligation? So the
רמב"ם Rambam says, well, going back to a גמרא Gemara we saw
before, if you accept upon yourself נזירות, nezirut, you will wind up
bringing a חטאת chattat and an אשם asham under some circumstances, so
that ultimately does or under certainly when the נזירות nezirut ends. Anyway,
that ultimately does can come through a free will act that you
have done. Okay, so the רמב"ם, Rambam, but even
most, most חטאת chattat and אשם.
asham. No no no, so then he says and that's why תרומה
terumah and חלה challah don't work because תרומה terumah and חלה challah
are an obligation. They are not a, they're not a type of,
you know, initiated by you free will type of an act. So
what's really fascinating about that besides answering our question about חלה challah
is that you know I've been talking all along that the גמרא
Gemara here makes us forget the biblical concept of נדר neder or
the you know which is in the end it does result in
an object being offered, but it starts with a person sort of
willingly saying I'm going to dedicate something to God, I'm going to
obligate myself and then that's the myself to give something. But again,
a נדר neder you take an obligation to give a קרבן, korban,
a נדר neder יעקב Yaakov takes a נדר neder to give מעשר.
ma'aser. It starts and that's why we have the concept of נדרי
מצוה. nidrei mitzvah. You can take a נדר neder to do a
מצוה mitzvah which is about a personal obligation, right? So although the
focus here is object, the biblical נדר neder starts with a personal
obligation and ends with an object. And the רמב"ם Rambam brings it
back to that. that biblical sort of paradigm, that דבר הנדור, davar
hanadur, something that started with a personal free-will offering. So that's point
number one. Relatedly, I wanted to say before we continued on in
the גמרא Gemara since we have a little bit extra time, that
this is an important issue that the ר"ן Ran raises at the
very beginning of the מסכת, masechet, which is עד שידור בדבר הנדור.
ad sheyidor bedavar hanadur. It seems to me, it has seemed to
me, that that is the paradigm, like I said. Like if you
wanted to ask what is the classic language of a נדר, neder,
the classic language of a נדר neder is, you know, קונם דבר
זה עלי konam davar zeh alai or קרבן דבר זה עלי, korban
davar zeh alai, but using a כינוי kinuy קונם. konam. Okay. If
you say, you know, פת זה אסורה עלי, pat zeh asurah alai,
is forbidden to me, without the word קונם, konam, then that presumably
works as a יד, yad, that's because it's implicit the idea of
קרבן korban although not stated. But that the classic language would be
a language of קרבן. korban. The ר"ן Ran actually raises that question
on the very first דף, daf, whether the classic language is קונם
konam and when you just say דבר זה אסור, davar zeh assur,
it's a יד yad to the full statement, or no, maybe actually
just saying דבר זה אסור davar zeh assur is a full statement.
And the הלכה halacha of דבר הנדור davar hanadur is if you
choose to use the idea of modeling it after another object, you
have to use a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur, not a דבר האסור.
davar haassur. But you don't actually, that's not actually a conceptual part
of making the נדר neder altogether. Conceptually the נדר neder is just
דבר זה אסור, davar zeh assur, like לאסור איסר על נפשו, leesur
issar al nafsho, which is the end of the פסוק. pasuk. If
you only say דבר זה אסור, davar zeh assur, that's the classic
language. The use of some other object is an optional thing and
if you do it, it has to be in a certain way,
it has to be דבר הנדור davar hanadur but not דבר האסור.
davar haassur. So take a look, the ר"ן Ran repeats that here
and it says, it's אמר קרא כי ידור נדר, amar kra ki
yidor neder, it's about ten lines before the lines get middle-sized here
in the ר"ן. Ran. Okay. אמר קרא כי ידור נדר עד שידור
בדבר הנדור נראה בעיני דהכי פירושו דסבירא ליה לש"ס דלאשמעינן דמתפיס בדבר
הנדור מיתסר לא צריך קרא דכיון
amar kra ki yidor neder ad sheyidor bedavar hanadur nireh
beeinai dehachi peirusho desvira lei leShas delashmieinan dematpis bedavar hanadur mitasair lo
tzarich kra dekeivan that
you don't need a פסוק pasuk to tell you that you can
use the idea of a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur, דכיון דאמר כיכר
זה עלי אסור, dekeivan deamar kikar zeh alai assur,
as long as you said this loaf of bread is forbidden to
me, הוי נדר, havei neder, that would be a נדר. neder. כי
אמר נמי כקרבן אסור כקרבן אסור קאמר דלא גרע מידות. ki amar
nami kekorban assur kekorban assur kaamar delo gara miyidot.
So therefore if you said כיכר זה כקרבן, kikar zeh kekorban, that
would also be forbidden because it's no worse than a יד. yad.
So this ר"ן Ran is like amazing! He says if you say
כיכר זה כקרבן, kikar zeh kekorban, you know why it's אסור? assur?
'Cause that's a יד yad to the statement כיכר זה אסור עלי,
kikar zeh assur alai, that the actual classic statement of a נדר
neder is כיכר זה אסור עלי. kikar zeh assur alai. And when
you say קרבן, korban, that's actually just a יד yad for the
real way of saying it, which is דבר זה אסור. davar zeh
assur. So I think that's a really fascinating question, right, which is
the classic? Is the classic to say דבר זה קרבן davar zeh
korban or קונם konam and when you say אסור assur it's a
יד yad and you imply the idea of קרבן? korban? Or is
the classic saying אסור assur and then if you say קרבן korban
that also works as a substitute, as a, you know, as a
shorthand for that idea. So to me again conceptually, you know, it's
very powerful that your power to make something forbidden, to give it
a הלכה-ic halacha status of forbidden, you know, sort of is rooted
in that power of speech you have to like make something forbidden
as a קרבן. korban. So to me I want to see that
as the paradigm, you know, and everything else like a shorthand for
that. But the ר"ן Ran actually says no, maybe the חידוש chiddush
of the תורה Torah of a נדר neder is not that it
borrows from a power you have somewhere else. You fundamentally through your
act of speech can make something forbidden, okay, and you can just
say דבר זה אסור. davar zeh assur. That's your power to make
a נדר. neder. You don't need to evoke any other power or
invoke any other power. But if you actually say דבר זה קור,
davar zeh kor, if you want to use a model of something
else, it has to be consistent with this idea of something made
through your speech act. But actually fundamentally your power to make a
נדר neder is an intrinsic power to make something forbidden through your
speech act.
דבר זה אסור עלי כקרבן? davar zeh assur alai kekorban? Then you're
just, yeah, then
you're saying way too much, right. כקרבן, kekorban, עלי אמי. alai imi.
Right.
You can either say, right, you can either say דבר זה קונם
davar zeh konam or דבר זה אסור. davar zeh assur. Either one
of those words works. The question is which is the primary statement
and which is the one that
just, that just, right, exactly.
All right. So that I thought was really interesting. All right. Let's
take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues. So now the משנה
mishnah goes on and it says if somebody says my wife is
forbidden to me like my mother, okay, so we're going to find
out that a man can make having sex with his wife forbidden
to him or a woman making sex with her husband forbidden to
her, even though there are obligations and מצוות mitzvot and etc., 'cause
that's the idea that a נדר neder is חל על דבר מצוה.
chal al devar mitzvah. You don't directly say I'm going to not
do what I'm obligated to do, you just make the object forbidden,
and here the object is the other person and they're forbidden regarding
the sexual pleasure one would derive. That's again the idea that you
can make an object be- the object could be a part of
a person's body or a person's body and what's forbidden doesn't have
to just be food or הנאה hanaah in general, it could be
a specific type of a benefit. Okay. So that's if, yes, so
that would be if somebody said קונם. konam. קונם הנאת תשמישך עלי.
konam hanas tashmishcha alay. Okay, so that would be a נדר neder
that would make it forbidden, but here the person did not use
the word קרבן korban and he didn't just say the word אסור,
assur, he said like my mother is forbidden to me. So that
is מתפיס בדבר האסור matfis bedavar ha'assur not דבר הנדור. davar hanadur.
Yes.
I'm just saying that in that case it's not the person is
not forbidden but the act that's
forbidden.
Right. Right. Right.
As a result of, as a result of that the sex, as
a result of the sexual pleasure being forbidden, the person cannot engage
in sex because then he would have violated that status. That's correct.
Okay, so the Gemara says like this: רמינהו, raminhu, I'll ask you
on this. Oh, but the Mishnah ends by saying that we do
make, make the person go through a process of התרת נדרים hataras
nedarim so he should not be lenient. And the Ran says specifically
because it's clear that people would,
that this would be a not uncommon thing for people to make
the sex of their wife forbidden to them or possibly the other
direction as well when they would get angry with their partner. So
therefore if we said don't worry about this one because it was
דבר האסור, davar ha'assur, it would come to him not worrying about
it when he did it in the right way, you know, and
as a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur, just simply said forbidden. So that's
why we make him go through this process of התרת נדרים. hataras
nedarim. So the Gemara says רמינהו, raminhu, I'll ask you on this.
What's just happened here? Oh,
hold on. That's weird. I'm sorry.
Something weird is happening here. I'm sorry everybody just give me a
second.
My computer's acting flaky on me.
Oh gosh. None of
this.
No, whatever.
Okay, there we go. All right, so anyway,
okay. So it said, so the Gemara says like this: רמינהו, raminhu,
I'll ask you on this. הרי את עלי כבשר אמא, harei at
alay kevasar ima, הרי
כבשר אחותי, harei kevasar achoti, you're forbidden to me like my mother...
actually here it's much more, yeah, flesh, it's much more, I don't
know, graphic or physical. Anyway, my, my sister's flesh,
כערלה ככלאי הכרם, ke'orlah kekiley hakerem, which I think that are forbidden
in הנאה. hana'ah. לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, it's meaningless, even
though they say oh my god, I mean it's, he wants her
to treat it like incest or whatever, you know, it doesn't exactly
matter because that's not the, because again, that's the principle of דבר
הנדור. davar hanadur. Okay,
so the Gemara says לא אמר כלום. lo amar klum. אמר אביי,
amar Abaye, so, okay,
so what's the problem? So the problem is that לא אמר כלום
lo amar klum sounds like you don't have to worry about it
at all, whereas our Mishnah says you have to go through a
process of התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. So the Gemara says אמר אביי
לא אמר כלום מדאורייתא, amar Abaye lo amar klum mide'oraisa, fine,
biblically it's nothing, וצריך שאלה מדרבנן, vetsarich she'elah miderabbanan, but rabbinically you
have to go through this process. רבא אמר, Rava amar, Rava says,
הא בתלמידי חכמים הא בעם הארץ. ha betalmidey chachamim ha be'am ha'aretz.
Ah,
so this point that we make you go through a process of
התרת נדרים, hataras nedarim, you know because it is interesting, right, the
Mishnah doesn't say it's אסור מדרבנן, assur miderabbanan, right it says you
need to go through a process of התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. So
אסור מדרבנן assur miderabbanan would be funny to say for some people
it's אסור מדרבנן assur miderabbanan and for other people it's not. But
here we're not actually saying technically it's אסור, assur, we're saying we
require you to go through this process of התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim.
So there you could say, we're requiring it for people that are
going to be too sloppy, we're not requiring it for people that
will know, will understand. You know, of course if you're such a
תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, why did you say כבשר אמא? kebasar ima?
Unless, unless maybe you said it because you knew it wouldn't be
binding, that was a way to sort of vent your anger but
you knew it wouldn't be binding, I don't know. Anyway, let's read
a minute. Okay, it says הא בעם הארץ והא בתלמידי חכמים. ha
be'am ha'aretz ve'ha betalmidey chachamim. So the Gemara says והתניא, vehatanya, and
we taught similarly in a Baraita, והתניא vehatanya often introduces a challenge,
but sometimes it introduces a support. And again, it is my feeling
that I haven't checked this out, but that in נדרים, Nedarim, which
again is a different type, uses a different type of language than
the other מסכתות, masechtos, that והתניא vehatanya actually is much more often
a support rather than a challenge. I'm pretty sure that's true in
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi as well, that anyway והתניא, vehatanya, so we taught
similarly in a Baraita, הנודר בתורה לא אמר כלום, hanoder batorah lo
amar klum, that if somebody takes a vow with the Torah, I'm
going to unpack this in a minute but let's just sort of
see how it's being brought. He didn't say anything, ואמר רבי יוחנן
וצריך שאלה לחכם, ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan vetsarich she'elah lechacham, because let's just
start with the idea that a Torah's not a דבר הנדור, davar
hanadur, whatever status the Torah has, it's because you know of the
קדושה kedushah of a ספר תורה sefer torah is not a קדושה
kedushah that you sort of have verbally instilled in the Torah. So
therefore it's not a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur,
no matter how holy it is, ואמר רבי יוחנן וצריך שאלה לחכם,
ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan vetsarich she'elah lechacham, you have to go through a
process of התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. So ואמר רב נחמן ותלמיד חכם
אינו צריך שאלה, ve'amar Rav Nachman vetalmid chacham eyno tsarich she'elah, but
a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham doesn't have to. So here you have
an exact reflection of all three statements being made: לא אמר כלום,
lo amar klum, nothing, which sounds like you can just not worry
about it; then you need a, you need to go through a
process of התרת נדרים, hataras nedarim, so you can say both לא
אמר כלום lo amar klum and you need a process of התרת
נדרים; hataras nedarim; and the idea that a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
doesn't need it, so therefore that might also reinforce the language of
לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, at least in principle. Yes, Charlie.
What's a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham doing making a נדר neder that
doesn't take?
Yeah, so I just said that before.
So at least by the case of his wife, you know, you
could say that I have no At
least in case of his wife you could say that it’s what
do you call it, that it’s a way of venting his anger,
but maybe look, maybe the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham but he never
learned נדרים. nedarim. I mean, we’ve got the גאונים ge’onim said they
didn’t learn נדרים nedarim in the ישיבות. yeshivos. I know a lot
of תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim that don’t know too much about נדרים.
nedarim. Yes. Do they translate רמינהי reminhi
or ורמינהו ureminhu or מיתיבי meisivei the same way? Yeah, there’s one
brings a קשיא kashya from a משנה mishna and the other from
a ברייתא?
braisa? That is a good question. Is there a technical difference between
that? רמינהי reminhi is often a text showing a contradiction from a
different text,
like a contradiction of two texts. Yeah, I’m not sure specifically about
ורמינהו ureminhu or מיתיבי. meisivei. Lynn, you know? You have any thoughts?
Lynn is an academic תלמיד talmid there. No.
So ורמינהי reminhi is from an earlier source and מיתיבי meisivei comes
from a source from the same period, like a ברייתא braisa against
a ברייתא, braisa, a ברייתא braisa against a משנה? mishna? Interesting. All
right, we’ll have to check that out. Yes.
But the interesting thing is תלמיד חכם talmid chacham versus עם הארץ,
am ha’aretz, it’s not in my mind, or shouldn’t be in my
mind, based on knowledge, it should be based on personality, right? If
we’re worried דלא לירגיל עצמו בכך, d’lo l’yargil atzmo b’kach, like you
don’t want you to be like אוסר oser your wife on you
or something like that, or just like סתם stam קופץ בנדרים, kofetz
b’nedarim, it’s just like you really shouldn’t be doing this, taking your
words lightly, taking maybe God lightly, taking all these things lightly. So
it shouldn’t be really a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham better control themselves,
is that what they’re saying?
So I don’t understand, what are you saying?
Like why does it say תלמיד חכם? talmid chacham? I don’t think
it’s as much
because...
Well, if the idea is we don’t want you making these vows
all together, then you’re right, then there wouldn’t be a difference. But
the ר"ן ran explains it that, and you could say that, like
we don’t want men making vows against their wives, wives against their
husbands, so we’re always going to make it a pain to whatever,
we’re going to make it, it won’t be trivial to undo it.
Yeah, you could have read it that way, but because of this
תלמיד חכם talmid chacham aspect, the ר"ן ran is reading it that
it’s a concern about
that you’ll come to figure that next that you don’t have to
worry about the vows you make, not that we don’t want you
making vows, but you will feel you won’t have to worry about
the vows, you’ll extrapolate from this to other vows which really are
binding.
Yeah, the ר"ן ran gets the impression that עמי הארץ amei ha’aretz
were considered to be careful of, fastidious about observing נדרים. nedarim. Ah,
this right? Why?
Oh, because the reaction like, okay, if
this will cause you to be מיקל ראש, meikel rosh, but if
it weren’t for this as a general rule you wouldn’t be מיקל
ראש. meikel rosh. Right, that could be,
that’s a good point. All right, yes, one more question.
Seems that the support of a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham does not
need שאלה she’ela is not part of the ברייתא braisa because it
was quoted in the name of רב
נחמן. Rav
Nachman. The second,
the והתניא. ve-hatanya. Right, correct. Those statements of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and רב נחמן Rav Nachman were clarifying that ברייתא. braisa. That is
correct. So the same way, so the same way we have אמוראים
amora’im clarifying the משנה, mishna, you have אמוראים amora’im clarifying the ברייתא.
braisa. That is correct. That’s a very good point. Okay, so now
the גמרא, gemara, so now this question about if הנודר בתורה לא
אמר כלום. hanoder b’Torah lo amar klum. Let’s see what the גמרא
gemara does with this and we’ll have two very interesting reads of
what this means. So for now we’re taking it like the simple
sense, that you say כיכר זה עלי כתורה, kikar zeh alai k’Torah,
okay, which is pretty funny, תורה Torah first of all isn’t, I
mean it’s קדושה kedusha you have to handle in a certain way,
but first of all it’s not like אסור בהנאה assur b’hana’ah and
it’s certainly not a דבר הנדור. davar hanadur. So okay, that’s why
לא אמר כלום. lo amar klum. But now let’s see what we
have on the, as we turn the דף daf on יד עמוד
ב. yud daled amud beis. תניא, tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא: braisa: הנודר בתורה לא אמר כלום. hanoder b’Torah lo amar klum.
Somebody who makes a נדר neder with the תורה Torah has not
said anything. ובמה שכתוב בה דבריו קיימין. uv’mah shekasuv bah devarav kayamin.
But if you say this is forbidden with what is written in
the תורה, Torah, your words are established. Now, what does that mean?
Why, what’s במה שכתוב בה? mah shekasuv bah? The words, the words
have קדושה kedusha that the תורה Torah doesn’t and why is that
a דבר הנדור? davar hanadur?
Sounds like to me like this is אסור assur like something else
that’s forbidden by the words of the תורה. Torah.
Ah, very good, like קרבנות korbanos you mean, which would be a
דבר הנדור. davar hanadur. Well, it couldn’t be like חזיר, chazir, it’s
נדר neder is אסור assur like any דאורייתא. de’oraisa.
Yeah, but then it would be like בשר חזיר. basar chazir. Okay,
so let’s keep on reading and then we’ll have three interesting explanations
of this. Okay, the בבלי, Bavli, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and then whatever.
ובה ובמה שכתוב בה. uvah uv’mah shekasuv bah. So if you say
with it and what’s written in it, דבריו קיימין, devarav kayamin, that
also works. So now the גמרא gemara is going to try to
understand why you needed the last phrase. קתני במה שכתוב בה דבריו
קיימין, בה ובמה שכתוב
בה צריך למימר?
kasani b’mah shekasuv bah devarav kayamin,
bah uv’mah shekasuv bah tzarich l’meimar? So once you say what’s written
in it it works, certainly to say it and what’s written in
it it should work. So אמר רב נחמן amar Rav Nachman לא
קשיא. lo kashya. הא דמנחא
אורייתא אארעא,
הא דנקיט לה בידיה.
ha d’mancha oraissa a-ara,
ha d’nakit lah bidei. Is it on the ground or are you
holding onto it? מנחא אארעא, mancha a-ara, if it’s on the ground,
I don’t know what you’re doing with your תורה Torah on the
ground, but let’s say okay it’s on the... the table, so anyway,
yeah, I understand. גיטי אגוילי. Geitei agvilei. So even if you say
במה שכתוב בה, Bemah shekasuv bah, it doesn't work because you're thinking
about the parchment. Now, how is במה שכתוב בה Bemah shekasuv bah
thinking about the parchment? That's thinking about what's in the parchment. But
no, the question is how you read that sentence. It could be
במה Bemah with what שכתוב shekasuv that is written, you know,
on it. Not, I mean, no, I misstated that. במה שכתוב, Bemah
shekasuv,
I am forbidding it במה Bemah with what שכתוב בה. shekasuv bah.
Hold on, let me get this straight again. גיטי אגוילי. Geitei agvilei.
Hold on, how would you make this be the parchment?
On that thing, no, on that thing that the words are written
on. במה Bemah on that thing שכתוב בה shekasuv bah that things
are written in on it. Okay, so on the object, on the
parchment which the words are written on it, okay? So somehow you
could get במה שכתוב בה Bemah shekasuv bah to mean the parchment
if it's on the ground, because then somehow that shows less, I
don't know, somehow less of a connection to it. I don't understand
why it matters whether it's on the ground or you're holding it,
how to read the phrase.
The ר״ן Ran says רש״י Rashi says something here. Yeah. Because if
it's on the ground, then it's probably nothing written on it.
Oh, that's interesting. Okay, I don't know about that then. Anyway, okay.
מסתמא גיטי אגוילי. Mistama geitei agvilei. נקיט ליה בידיה Nakit leh biyadei
when you're holding it, דעתיה
אהזכרות שבה. daateih al hazkaros shebah. Then במה
שכתוב בה
Bemah shekasuv
bah you mean what's writ, the things that are written in it,
not the things that are being written on, the things that are
in it, which is the God's name. And I just want to
stop there for a minute because that's going to help us go
back and understand how the נדר neder works. So what do you
mean, so it says, it says when you say במה שכתוב בה
Bemah shekasuv bah it works because you're referring to God's name. Now,
how is God's name a דבר הנדור? davar hanadur? Right? God's name
isn't a דבר הנדור. davar hanadur. קדושה Kedusha God's name is not
through your verbal speech. So the ר״ן Ran suggests two answers. Answer
number one is we're not talking about a נדר. neder. And this
is so ironic, right, because so much of the effort is to
distinguish between נדר neder and שבועה. shvua. But we also know that
sometimes it uses the word הנודר, hanoder, which means somebody who takes
a שבועה. shvua. So he says הנודר בתורה Hanoder baTorah and this
you completely can understand, completely understand the phenomenon he's describing. Somebody says,
hold onto a ספר תורה sefer torah and says 'In the name
of this תורה,' Torah, you know, like put your hand on the
Bible, right? Where you put your hand on the Bible and then
you swear in the name of God, right? So here you're not
swearing in the name of God, you're just holding onto the תורה.
Torah. 'In the name of this תורה Torah I will do such
a thing.' Okay, so here נודר noder meaning take a שבועה, shvua,
which is obviously a radical shift from the whole focus we've been
having about דבר הנדור. davar hanadur. But then the issue is, okay,
when you say 'In this תורה' Torah do you just mean the
physical תורה? Torah? Then you're not taking a שבועה בשם ה׳. shvua
beshem Hashem. Do you mean in what is written in the תורה,
Torah, in the name of God that is in this תורה? Torah?
So you're taking a שבועה בשם ה׳. shvua beshem Hashem. That's במה
שכתוב בה. Bemah shekasuv bah. So that's a very nice explanation. We
don't have to worry about דבר הנדור, davar hanadur, we just have
to say נודר noder here means take a שבועה, shvua, which it
does sometimes.
Right. One minute. Now the other explanation is a fascinating one, which
is the ראב״ד Raavad says that even though שם ה׳, Shem Hashem,
you don't just come around and say 'I'm instilling in you the
קדושה kedusha of שם ה׳,' Shem Hashem, but because it requires the
כוונה kavana of the סופר sofer when he writes it, here becomes
an interesting question. Do we say that the סופר sofer is instilling,
like the סופר sofer has to think, like he has, you know,
with the קדושה kedusha of שם ה׳, Shem Hashem, you know, that
he's writing the God's name, that his כוונה kavana is important to
give it the שם ה׳? Shem Hashem? So do we say that
to some degree it's him instilling the קדושה kedusha in the name?
Or do we say, 'No, no, no, if he writes it somehow
with the right כוונה kavana and he creates the proper שם ה׳
Shem Hashem done properly, then like as it were the תורה Torah
sort of recognizes it as קדוש.' kadosh. But it's not a קדושה
kedusha that he instilled in it. You have a similar question, I
know it's a little radical shift, but the whole idea that the
writing of a גט get by the husband requires it to be
done לשמה, lishmah, it's for the sake of his wife. And there's
an interesting discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim and in the אחרונים Acharonim
to what degree is it seen like that he's instilling in the
גט get its directedness towards his wife? It's לשמה. lishmah. And the
relevant aspect is because there's a concept that a husband can nullify
a גט. get. What does it mean he can nullify a גט
get once the גט get was, meaning before it's been delivered to
the woman, not just nullify his שליח, shaliach, an agent that he
made, but he sort of says 'I am now making the גט
get void.' How do you make a גט get void just by
saying you're making it void? You know, if you wanted to make
a check void, you'd have to like tear it up, right? So
if so, there's an idea that he instilled in it its sort
of directedness towards his wife and therefore he can, he can reverse
that. So similarly the ראב״ד Raavad suggests here that even though it
requires being written, we sort of see that it's that he is
still the one instilling the קדושה kedusha in it. Now it's still
not totally through a speech act. Now it's a speech act that's
coming with, you know, with
a physical act, but nevertheless if we sort of see it originating
in his instilling in it, that might be considered to be like
דבר הנדור. davar hanadur. It's like similar, you know, when we've been
discussing for a minute the... Idea of like תרומה, trumah, although תרומה
trumah isn't actually seen as דבר הנדור; davar hanadur; but nevertheless, something
that if I needed to let's say physically separate the תרומה trumah
and designate it. Would we consider that a דבר הנדור? davar hanadur?
Right? How much is it that it could be just totally through
speech? Or do we say, no, even if it requires an act,
if fundamentally the status is being sort of imparted through the speech,
even if an act has to come with it, that still makes
it a דבר הנדור. davar hanadur. So that's how Ravyad understood that
the אזכרות azkarot are exactly a דבר הנדור. davar hanadur. The שם
השם Shem Hashem in the ספר תורה Sefer Torah has a קדושה
kedusha that a person instilled and created, and therefore he could say,
"This is like the שם השם." Shem Hashem. The other interesting part
about that is that the שם השם, Shem Hashem, it's not like
it's אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. I mean, it is קדוש. kadosh. I
mean, you use it for reading. Obviously you want to—go ahead—I mean,
it has קדושה, kedusha, but we don't normally think about it as,
"Oh, a Torah is אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah but you can read
it because מצות לאו להנות ניתנו." mitzvot lav lehanot nitnu. I mean,
we don't think of it as אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. קדושה kedusha
demands a certain type of treatment of it. It has a status,
but not an אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah status. So that's also interesting.
Yes, Dov?
This
is extremely powerful, so we're talking about a speech act. Right. So
this raises the question of what is speech that's confined or ossified
in a written form, right? What is the relationship to a speech
act? So they're kind of so vivified.
I mean, that's a good point too, that here you're not just
doing any act, it's not like separating off תרומה. trumah. The act
you're doing is actually writing down the speech, as it were. So
it's actually a concretization of the speech. Oh, right, although the סופר
sofer never said those words, right? It's still like his thoughts, but
yes. Thoughts being physically—being physically—that's a very good point. Right. In a
way maybe even better than my example of like the תרומה, trumah,
because maybe again, it's his sort of thoughts being physically concretized. So
it's an interesting—yes.
Where's that brought?
So it's quoted in the ר"ן. Ran. The ר"ן Ran says like
this, he says, "Wait
a minute, let's find it." Pernov's?
I think so. One
minute.
Yeah, four lines down from the widest line. He says, אבל הראב"ד
ז"ל פירש דהכי תני נודר נודר ממש קאמר שאומר כיכר זה עלי
כתורה ולא אמר כלום לפי שאין מתפיס אלא בגבולין. Aval HaRa'avad zal
peireish de-hachi tani noder noder mamash ka’amar she-omer kikar zeh alai ke-Torah
velo amar klum lefi she-ein matpis ela bi-gvilin. Parchment. אבל אמר במה
שכתוב בה כלומר כיכר זה עלי במה שכתוב בה הרי זו אסור
כמתפיס בדבר הנדור משום דדעתיה אזכרות.
Aval amar be-mah she-katuv bah klomar kikar zeh alai be-mah she-katuv bah
harei zo asur ke-matpis be-davar ha-nadur mishum de-da'ateih azkarot. ואזכרות שבה נודרין
הן או נדורין הן סליחה שעל ידי הכתיבה והכנה לשם קדושה הן
קדושות.
Ve-azkarot she-bah nodrin hein o nedurin hein
selicha she-al yedei ha-ketivah ve-hachanah le-sheim kedushah hein kedushot.
Right.
Okay. So it's actually your instilling קדושה. kedusha. Now the third possibility,
which is not in the גמרא Gemara because the גמרא Gemara focused
on שם השם, Shem Hashem, it's in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi is that—I
think whoever it was that said, Dov was that you saying—like the
things that are forbidden in the Torah? So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi does
a twist on that. So let's keep on reading. והביא ראיה מן
הירושלמי דבנדר קאמר ולא בשבועה אבל בנדר הירושלמי דנהיג הוא אחר. Ve-heivi
re'ayah min ha-Yerushalmi de-ve-neder ka'amar velo bi-shvuah aval be-neder ha-Yerushalmi de-nehig hu
acher. דגרסינן התם בתורה לא אמר כלום במה שכתוב בה אסור כקימין
בתורה בקדושת התורה. De-garsinan hatam ba-Torah lo amar klum be-mah she-katuv bah
asur ke-kayamin ba-Torah bi-kdushat ha-Torah.
If you said "the sanctity of the Torah," then לא אמר כלום,
lo amar klum, the sanctity of the Torah is not a דבר
הנדור. davar hanadur. But במה שכתוב בה. be-mah she-katuv bah. So what's
written in the Torah? קרבנות הכתובין בה. Korbanot ha-ketuvin bah.
Okay! So there's קרבנות korbanot mentioned in the Torah! So therefore it's
no worse than saying בירושלים. bi-Yerushalayim. Right? בירושלים bi-Yerushalayim isn't a דבר
הנדור, davar hanadur, but you mean the—you're referring to things that are
brought in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, קרבנות korbanot that are brought. It's a way
of referring
to the fact the house is there.
Right. So presumably the fact that it also includes—either we assume you
mean קרבנות korbanot סתם נדרים להחמיר—we're stam nedarim lehachmir going to interpret
it, or the fact that it includes all those things it also
includes קרבנות. korbanot. Right? By the way, I did want to mention
that, which is Michael says, which is an interesting point. Let's say
somebody
says, let's say somebody says, "הרי זה עלי כקרבן וכבשר חזיר." Harei
zeh alai ke-korban u-ke-vasar chazir. Right? You can imagine somebody saying that,
right? They really want to make it forbidden. This is so forbidden
on me like עבודה זרה avodah zarah and חזיר chazir and קרבנות.
korbanot. Right? Would the fact that one of those words, right, is
the magical word, as it were, that does it, right? And the
other words, does the דבר הנדור davar hanadur somehow the דבר האסור
davar ha-assur somehow like, right, somehow make it a non-נדר neder or
it's just not powerful enough to make it a נדר? neder? It
would seem to me that it's not somehow undermined that as long
as you actually use the right thing, this doesn't make it like
less of a נדר neder the fact that you're also saying a
sort of a meaningless part of a statement. And I think that
that suggests and that would answer what you're saying. So במה שכתוב
בתורה be-mah she-katuv ba-Torah includes a lot of things, but among them
קרבנות. korbanot. The fact that the גמרא Gemara says it's obvious if
you say במה שכתוב בה, be-mah she-katuv bah, then you should certainly
if you say בה ובמה שכתוב בה. bah u-ve-mah she-katuv bah. Why
is it obvious? When you add something else, you're adding something that's
not a דבר הנדור, davar hanadur, right? If במה שכתוב בה be-mah
she-katuv bah is a problem because of the שם השם, Shem Hashem,
and you say בה ובמה שכתוב בה, bah u-ve-mah she-katuv bah, maybe
it's not a נדר neder because you said with the שם השם
Shem Hashem and
with— formula and then you added in something else, interestingly the גמרא
Gemara takes it as obvious that it doesn't create a problem. To
me it's not so obvious. Anyway, three very interesting explanations about why
the במה שכתוב בה b'ma she-kasuv ba works. Either it's a שבועה,
shvuah, not a נדר, neder, it's a נדר neder and the קדושת
שם השם kedusha shem Hashem is considered to be a דבר הנדור,
davar ha-nadur, which I think is a real fascinating idea and we
should also note again that it's not really something that's אסור בהנאה,
assur b'hana'ah, just has קדושה, kedusha, and the third possibility is that
you're referring to the קרבנות, korbanot, which is the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Yes,
Dove.
I'm not happy with the first one, the bit between שבועה shvuah
and נדר neder because on דף י"ד daf yod dalet is when
we had the איזהו איסור שבתורה eizehu issur she-ba-Torah when we talked
about כיום שמת אבי kiyom she-meis avi or יום שנהרג גדליה בן
אחיקם, yom she-neherag Gedaliah ben Ahikam,
right?
So it's obvious this thing was a שבועה, shvuah, but we had
to do backflips because on it's on דבר שבועה davar shvuah which
is נדר באסור הבא, neder b'issur ha-ba, right? But maybe not. Right,
very שבועה-esque.
shvuah Yeah, it is true, I know, it is true that most
of the time we want נדר neder to mean נדר neder and
the and it's true the ירוש... the בבלי often has opportunities to
say it means a שבועה shvuah and it doesn't go down that
route. But there still is the reality that sometimes, I mean if
you look at the ברייתות baraitas and the תוספתות toseftas and משניות
mishnayos and in that article by Saul Lieberman I sent out he
shows that as well, you know, it's clear that with all the
attempt to create this technical distinction, sometimes it's just used the vernacular
of הנודר. ha-noder. And as we said the other day, right, when
talking about התרת נדרים, hatarat nedarim, you know, are we really talking
about a נדר? neder? To some degree we are because we spoke
about נדרי מצווה nidrei mitzvah and נדרי מצווה nidrei mitzvah sort of
also cross that line. נדרי מצווה nidrei mitzvah is really has the
pat... is really effectively a שבועה, shvuah, it's about what I'm going
to do, right? But it's still in the נדר neder category.
That echoes Rabbi Dove's observation that the מסכת masechet is so particular
about language.
Right, exactly. What can I tell you? All right, but that is
true.
But you know again, Lieberman's point is is that that the whole
a lot of the enterprise of חז"ל Chazal here was that was
that the populace was very, very loose and sloppy and used all
different types of things and they were trying to sort of rein
it in and get a hold on it. So, you know, some
of that stuff is still might still be out there. All right,
so let's take a look now. So the גמרא Gemara says, why
do you need to say בו ובמה שכתוב בה? bo u-ve-ma she-kasuv
ba? So one answer is are you holding it or is it
on the ground? If it's on the ground and you said במה
שכתוב בה, b'ma she-kasuv ba, somehow that means the parchment, meaning a...
it's a little grammatical twist how we get that to mean the
parchment. But number two, it's not exactly clear to me that why
when it's on the ground do you somehow less mean the meaningful
thing, I mean you're less connected to it so I don't know,
you're less focused on its contents or something, you're more focused on
it as an object. Anyway, but if you're holding it, then saying
במה שכתוב בה b'ma she-kasuv ba itself suffices.
זיקים בה. zikim ba. There you go. שכוח. shkoyach. ואי בעית אימא
ve-i ba'is eima if you want I can tell you דמחא אארעא,
de-macha'o ar'a, both of the cases are that it's on the ground.
והא קמשמע לן דאף גב דמחא אארעא כיון דאמר במה שכתוב בה
מהני.
ve-ha kamashma lan de-af
gav de-macha'o ar'a kivan de-amar b'ma she-kasuv ba mehani. וזו אין צריך
לומר זו קתני. ve-zu ein tzarich lomar zu katani. That's the easiest
answer, obviously. So, it doesn't matter, on the ground, in your hand,
either way, you say במה שכתוב בה b'ma she-kasuv ba works. So
why did it have to say בו ובמה שכתוב בה? bo u-ve-ma
she-kasuv ba? To tell you... that was just thrown in, not necessary.
ואי בעית אימא, ve-i ba'is eima, so answer number two is במה
שכתוב בה b'ma she-kasuv ba always works. Answer number one is במה
שכתוב בה b'ma she-kasuv ba by itself only works if you're holding
it. If it's on the ground you have to say בו ובמה
שכתוב בה. bo u-ve-ma she-kasuv ba. Answer number three, ואי בעית אימא
ve-i ba'is eima
כולא מציעתא kula metziata or some say כולא סיפא נמי דנקיטי ליה
בידיה. kula seifa nami de-nakti leh b'yadei. The whole thing is you're
holding it onto your hands. והא קמשמע לן ve-ha kamashma lan so
what's the idea of בו ובמה שכתוב בה? bo u-ve-ma she-kasuv ba?
כיון דנקיטי ליה בידיה kivan de-nakti leh b'yadei since you're holding in
your hands אף גב דלא אמר אלא בו כמאן דאמר במה שכתוב
בה דמי.
af gav de-lo amar ela
bo k'man de-amar b'ma she-kasuv ba dami. It's good enough to say
בו. bo. So this way of reading it says if you say
בו bo and it's on the ground or like on a table,
it doesn't work, then you mean the גוויל. gvil. If however, then
switching in the middle, if however you're holding onto it... or let's
say I'm sorry, we shouldn't say in the middle, or if you
say במה שכתוב בה b'ma she-kasuv ba and it's on the table
it does work. If however you're holding onto it, then בו ובמה
שכתוב בה bo u-ve-ma she-kasuv ba here, talking about precision, the ו
vav doesn't mean "and" but the ו vav means "or". So the
third statement, the first two statements on it are talking about it's
on a table. It's on a table, you say בו, bo, it
doesn't work, במה שכתוב בה b'ma she-kasuv ba it does. The third
statement is but if you're holding onto it, then whether you say
בו bo or במה שכתוב בה, b'ma she-kasuv ba, either one alone
suffices because you're holding onto it makes it clear that you're indicating
what's written in it, okay?
If you're holding onto it and you only say בו, bo, בו
bo is a יד. yad. Right.
Exactly. All right, anyway, three different versions somehow about whether you're referring
to it or to what's written in it. But the more interesting
question is why במה שכתוב בה b'ma she-kasuv ba actually works. Is
it working as a נדר? neder? Is שם השם shem Hashem דבר
הנדור? davar ha-nadur? Or is it working as a שבועה? shvuah? Okay,
now we go on.
Next
משנה. mishna. קונם שאני ישן, konam she-ani yashen, קונם שאני מדבר, konam
she-ani medaber, שאני מהלך. she-ani mehalech. So, if
Or a
man says to
his wife, or some have הגרסא לאשתו, HaGirsa L'ishto, האומר לאשה קונם
שאני משמשך, Ha'omer L'Isha Konam She'Ani Meshamshach, or a man says to
his wife, or some have
הגרסא לאשתו, HaGirsa L'ishto, קונם שאני משמשך. Konam She'Ani Meshamshach. So here
the scene seems to be pointing to all these things that it
lacks a physical object, right? It's talking about the action. Nevertheless, הרי
זה בלא יחל דברו, Harei Zeh Belo Yachel Dvaro, the prohibition of
לא יחל דברו Lo Yachel Dvaro applies, which is also an interesting
way of framing it because it could have just said אסור. Assur.
Okay, so we go from the משנה Mishna at the end of
the first פרק Perek where it says קונם פי מדבר עליך, Konam
Pi Medaber Alecha, where it just says the simple sense of אסור,
Assur, right? Forbidden. Right? Then it says interestingly you had in the
middle cases of things which were מותר. Mutar. You had this middle
case of הרי את עלי כאמא, Harei At Alai K'Ima, again the
whole issue of sex is coming up again, maybe helping explain what
this is doing in סדר נשים. Seder Nashim. And then we're back
to that anyway, but this משנה Mishna really is contrasting to the
last משנה Mishna of the previous פרק, Perek, that the last משנה
Mishna when you mentioned a body part we said אסור. Assur. Here
you didn't mention a body part and it says הרי זה בלא
יחל דברו, Harei Zeh Belo Yachel Dvaro, which sounds like it's even
worse. Okay, so let's try to understand this. איתמר, Itmar, let's see
the גמרא. Gemara. It was said
קונם עיני בשינה היום, Konam Einai BiSheina Hayom, so here it's not
a problem of a physical object. You specifically say my eyes are
or are קונם, Konam, אסור Assur regarding sleep today, אם אישן למחר,
Im Ishan LeMachar, if I sleep tomorrow. So basically what are you
supposed to do today? You don't know whether or not you're going
to sleep tomorrow. So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Rav, אל יישן היום שמא יישן למחר. Al Yishan Hayom Shema
Yishan LeMachar. So don't sleep today lest you come to sleep tomorrow.
Right? So you say I will be, my eyes are forbidden in
הנאה Hana'ah to me today regarding sleep, right, if I fall if
I go to sleep tomorrow. You're trying to get yourself, tomorrow is
your going to be your you're going to have to study an
all-nighter for your final, okay, on Tuesday. So you want in order
to encourage yourself to do it you're you're make a very weird
נדר. Neder. You should have just made a קונם Konam sleep on
yourself tomorrow, but what you did was you said that you're קונם
Konam today if you sleep tomorrow. So do we let you sleep
today and we say we'll trust you to be careful not to
fall asleep tomorrow? Okay, so as not to retroactively transgress your נדר.
Neder. So אמר רב יהודה אמר מה? Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Mah?
I'm sorry, what was that?
Can you make a נדר Neder on תנאי? Tnai? Yes you can
make a נדר Neder on תנאי. Tnai. Future?
Yes, I mean, yeah, no.
But then it's what you will do in the future. Here it
would retroactively determine whether you had transgressed today. Okay so what's the
story? אמר רב, Amar Rav, so רב Rav says we don't let
you fall asleep today because we're afraid that if you sleep today
you won't be careful about not falling asleep tomorrow, retroactively you'll transgress.
And then you'll certainly fall asleep tomorrow!
But it won't be a problem because you won't have violated your
נדר. Neder. You'll fail your final, that's true. רב נחמן אמר, Rav
Nachman Amar, יישן היום ולא חיישינן שמא יישן למחר. Yishan Hayom Velo
Chaishinan Shema Yishan LeMachar. No we trust you, you can sleep today
and we'll trust you to be careful about your נדר Neder tomorrow.
Okay, ומודי רב יהודה,
Umodei
Rav Yehuda, so okay, ומודי רב יהודה Umodei Rav Yehuda באומר קונם
עיני בשינה למחר אם אישן היום.
Be'omer Konam Einai BiSheina
LeMachar Im Ishan Hayom. How do you pronounce it?
אישן? Ishan? Sorry, אם אישן היום. Im Ishan Hayom. Okay, so my
eyes are forbidden sleep tomorrow if I sleep today. So basically today
is the תנאי Tnai and tomorrow is the נדר. Neder. Everybody agrees
in that case שישן היום, SheYishan Hayom, that you can go to
sleep today. Why? כי לא מזדהר בתנאה אבל באיסורא מזדהר. Ki Lo
Mizdahar BiTna'ah Aval Be'Issura Mizdahar. Because in that case, right, when it
comes to be tomorrow, here's the case. If I say if I
sleep today I won't sleep to- I'll take a- my eyes will
be forbidden on me tomorrow, so we'll say okay do what you
want today and if the נדר Neder kicks in tomorrow we trust
people to be careful about the נדרים. Nedarim. I mean there is
true there's a general sort of you know concern about טוב אשר
לא תדור משתדור ולא תשלם, Tov Asher Lo Tidor MiShetidor Velo Tishalem,
it's not good to be involved in נדרים Nedarim altogether etc., but
that doesn't lead to the fact that we basically say that if
you take a נדר Neder we're not going to trust you to
keep it. Okay, so therefore go you want to sleep today fine
go to sleep today we'll trust you to keep your נדר Neder
tomorrow. Nobody disagrees with that. The question is if your נדר Neder
was today do we let you violate as it were your נדר
Neder today and trust you to not satisfy the condition tomorrow to
make sure that the נדר Neder didn't take effect? Or do we
say by the time you get to tomorrow you're not in your
נדר Neder anymore, you're just in your תנאי? Tnai? So people are
not concerned like this act itself won't be the violation, this act
will mean that retroactively I will have violated and there we're afraid
people won't be careful enough in terms of that so we're going
to ensure that you don't sleep today because we won't trust
you. yashan, yashen, I always get that, yashen, no,
yashane, קונם Konam *Konam*, I know, I keep on flipping them, okay,
some type of a
dyslexia going on there,
the A
state of verb, it's AA like that.
Got it. Okay, קונם Konam שאני ישן *Konam she'ani yashan*, שאני מהלך
*she'ani mehalech*, that helps, שאני מהלך *she'ani mehalech*, שאני מדבר *she'ani medaber*
וכולי *vechulei*. Okay, so that's our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. היכי דמי *Heichi
dami*, what's the case? אילימא הכי קתני *Ileima hachi katani* שאני ישן
*she'ani yashan*, מי הוי נדרא *mi havei nedira*? How would that work?
Our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says it's חל *chal*. והתנן *Vehatnan*, we taught
חומר בשבועות *chomer bishvuot*, the שבועות *shvuot* are more weighty שהשבועה חלה
על דבר שיש בו ממש ועל דבר שאין בו ממש *she'hashvua chala
al davar she'yesh bo mamash veal davar she'ein bo mamash* מה שאין
כן בנדרים *mah sheken bindarim*, right? נדרים *Nedarim* doesn't take place on
something that is not physical. So basically here's the question we should
have asked right at the outset of our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*: How
do you make sleep forbidden, walking forbidden? נדר neder *Neder* needs something
physical. ושינה דבר שאין בו ממש הוא *Veshina davar she'ein bo mamash
hu*. אלא דאמר *Ella de'amar*, so how could the whole משנה Mishnah
*Mishnah* work? So what's the case of the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*? Must
be דאמר קונם עיני בשינה Konam einai besheina *de'amar konam einai besheina*.
Okay, my eyes are forbidden. So basically reading it like the last
משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* of the previous פרק perek.
*Perek*.
So it's אתמר *itmar* קונם עיני
בשינה
Konam
einai
besheina *konam einai besheina*, so sort of the same idea, right? Yeah,
well that was a debate of אמוראים *amorayim*, we're trying to explain
the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah*. All right, one minute. So anyway, so we
have to first of all to make the משנה mishna *Mishnah* make
sense, insert the idea that it's talking about your eyes like the
last משנה mishna *Mishnah* of the previous פרק *Perek*. So now, ואי
לא ישרה *ve'ee lo yashira*, so that's just solving one problem. ואי
לא ישרה *Ve'ee lo yashira*, but still if you just say my
eyes are always forbidden in sleep, מי שבקינן ליה עד דעביד איסורא
*mi shavkinan lei
ad de'avad issura*? Do we wait for him to transgress? I mean
we know he's going to transgress. Somebody cannot go their whole life
without sleeping. ואמר רבי יוחנן *Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan*, שבועה shvua. שלא יישן
*shvua she'lo
yishan*, oh my god I moved again, יישן *yishan*, שבועה shvua. שלא
יישן שלושה ימים *shvua she'lo yishan shelosha yamim*, מלקין אותו וישן לאלתר
*malkin oto ve'yashen le'alter*. So somebody says a שבועה shvua *shvua* that
I won't sleep for שלושה ימים *shelosha yamim*, you give him lashes
and he's allowed to sleep לאלתר *le'alter* because you know such a
שבועה *shvua* cannot be fulfilled, so it's right away considered to be
like a שבועת שוא *shvuat shav* or a שבועת שקר *shvuat shaker*
because there's no potential of the thing being fulfilled, and then he
can go ahead and go to sleep right away because the שבועה
*shvua* never took place right at the outset. Now by the way,
this is an interesting question of how that would play out by
a נדר neder, *Neder* because again, remember a שבועה *shvua* is about
me and my obligation. So if I take a שבועה *shvua* let's
say to contradict an obligation of the תורה *Torah*, if I'm trying
to say I will do something the תורה *Torah* says I can't
do, so it's not possible to take that obligation, the שבועה *shvua*
doesn't take effect. Similarly, if I try to say I won't sleep
and it's impossible for me not to sleep, conceptually the שבועה *shvua*
is going right up against what is humanly possible, so the שבועה
*shvua* doesn't take effect. Might be שבועת שוא *shvuat shav* or שבועת
שקר *shvuat shaker*, but it doesn't take effect, I can go to
sleep right away. But if I say נדר neder *neder* my eyes
are forbidden בשינה *besheina*, I have not directly contradicted, you
know,
some type of something the same way I don't directly contradict the
מצוה *mitzvah* by saying a סוכה *sukkah* is אסורה *asura*, כל סוכות
אסורה עלי *kol sukkot asura alai*, or all תפילין tefillin. *tefillin* is
אסור assur עלי *asur alai*, you know, because it will work out
that I won't be able to do what I'm obligated to do
if my eye is forbidden in sleep, it'll work out that I'm
going to sleep and I'm going to violate that נדר neder. *neder*,
but the actual taking of the vow does not directly contradict
an obligation or
something that's physically possible. So it is interesting that the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* makes that comparison.
There's a תוספות *Tosfot* here that says, if you take a look
at the תוספות *Tosfot*, ואי לא ישרה מי שבקינן עד דעביד איסורא
*ve'ee lo yashira mi shavkinan ad de'avad issura*, מכן פירשו דנדר שאי
אפשר לקיים אינו חל *mikan perushu de'neder she'iy efshar lekayem eino chal*.
You see this the far left corner column, דחל *de'chal*, דהכא מדמי
נדר neder שאי אפשר לקיים לשבועה שהיא שוא *de'hacha midami neder she'iy
efshar lekayem lishvua she'hi shav*. והוא דנדר מכל פרי דעלמא *Vehu deneder
mikol pri de'alma*, so how about if a person takes a vow
that he won't eat any fruit? Okay, I don't know why we
think it's אי אפשר לקיים *iy efshar lekayem*, you can go through
life not eating fruit. Okay, vegetables, I don't know. So לאו דוקא
כל פרי *lav davka kol pri*, דאם כן לא הוי חל כיון
דאי אפשר לקיים *de'im ken lo haye chal keivan de'iy efshar lekayem*.
Okay, but it's not so פשוט *pashut*, right? That's a big חידוש
*chiddush* because again, that's the conceptual difference between a נדר neder. *neder*
and a שבועה *shvua*. שבועה *Shvua* is I'm saying I'm going to
do something when I'm not able to do it or when I'm
obligated to do the opposite, so that's directly contradicted. I'm saying what
I'm doing when I'm supposed to do something else, or when I
can't do the thing that I'm telling myself that I'm saying I
have to do. There's a direct impossibility or contradiction, it doesn't take
effect. Whereas by a נדר neder *neder* it's indirect. I'm just saying
my eye is forbidden in שינה *sheina*. Ah, it's impossible for me
not to sleep? Well we'll worry about that when we get to
it. But right now conceptually, right? Like I say תפילין *tefillin* is
forbidden. Ah, you're obligated to put on תפילין *tefillin*? All right, but
I'm not talking about my obligation, I'm just talking about the תפילין
*tefillin*. I'm just talking about my eyes. Right? Now maybe you could
say I don't know, it's not in the physical ability of the
eye, well I mean if you want to think about it really
as a physical object, right? Well it will have to close in
terms of the physical nature of the eye. But as of now...
That's true, it's different than his example of the fruit. Right? If
I say all fruit is forbidden to me, even if we say
it's not humanly possible, all food in the world is forbidden to
me, so it's not all right all water is forbidden, it's not
humanly possible to live without that, but it's not in the physical
quality of the food in the world that it has to be
eaten by me, right? So it is a big חידוש here to
say that it doesn't take effect, and maybe it is specifically about
the eyes, maybe something about the eyes will necessarily close and go
to sleep, but it's not about the fact of whether I as
a person can or can't fulfill it. Yes?
Comparison to מצוות mitzvot is bothering me because it seems to me
that there's a difference between what I'm allowed and what I'm able.
Right, well that's my point. My point is correct, but at least
by מצוות mitzvot we have the idea of allowed and we show
that contradiction, and therefore we have a similar idea about able by
this idea of I won't sleep. But that all is so you're
right, they're not the same, but they're conceptually similar in it talking
about what you're trying to mandate yourself to be and what you're
allowed or able to do. But it's all about whether what you
are sort of you know what your what you are what you
know it's all about you and what you can and cannot do
as opposed to here there's one thing about what you can do
and there's another thing about what you're talking about in terms of
the object. Okay, so anyway it is interesting that here let me
just finish this. So it is interesting that the גמרא Gemara says
so it can't be that you said that you know I'm that
my eyes won't sleep because then הרי זה בבל יחל harei zeh
be'val yeichel means somehow like the נדר neder is binding and when
you transgress you transgress, but the גמרא Gemara is saying but that
wouldn't be true. If you said קונם my eyes I'll never you
know I'll always be forbidden in the sleep of my eyes, then
basically it shouldn't be binding at the outset because it's impossible to
fulfill, okay which is again what I've been pointing out a fascinating
idea that we talk about whether it's possible to fulfill or not
as relevant to a נדר, neder not just relevant to a שבועה.
So let me see if it's physically impossible then it's not you
know as opposed to physically it's it is possible for me to
not put on תפילין.
Right, so so
so it either does or it doesn't work, right?
Does not work.
So how the משנה mishna it does work?
Right, that was the question I was asking. Okay, so anyway so
the but so again it might have to do with the fact
that physically the eyes will close. So anyway the גמרא Gemara says
but that's not the comparison the גמרא Gemara is making. The גמרא
Gemara is making a comparison to שבועה. So that's what's particularly interesting.
Anyway the גמרא Gemara says if a person said my eyes are
always forbidden in sleep, it sounds like not that you are forbidden
and it's בבל יחל, bal yeichel, it sounds like it wouldn't take
effect at all because it's not possible. Okay
by the way if it really doesn't take effect would you get
punished for it? When the שבועה doesn't take effect it's a שבועת
שווא shvuat shav and you get מלקות, malkot, that's מלקינן ליה, malkinan
lei, right? You get מלקות, malkot, you can go to sleep right
away because it didn't take effect but you made a שבועת שווא.
shvuat shav. There's no איסור issur making a נדר שווא, shav, right?
So if it didn't take effect I get totally off scot-free? Is
that what it's saying? Fascinating. All right, I would have said when
you fall asleep you get מלקות. malkot. Anyway so wait wait let's
see the answer, hold on, גמרא Gemara says like this,
אלא דאמר קונם עיני בשינה למחר אם אישן היום.
ella de'amar Konam einai besheina lemachar im ishan
hayom.
So it's now again why we should say that's what the משנה
mishna means I have no idea, but maybe it's one of these
cases where we're trying to have the משנה say something interesting. So
if the משנה had just to say meant okay קונם עיני בשינה
Konam einai b'shina, for today, then it wouldn't מחדש mechadesh anything, that
was the משנה we had at the end of the last פרק.
קונם עיני בשינה works, okay, but it so it so must be
saying something more interesting than that. So it must be you're saying
קונם my eyes in sleep tomorrow if I sleep today, and הרי
זה בבל יחל, harei zeh be'val yeichel, and הרי זה בבל יחל
harei zeh be'val yeichel means that because we're concerned that you won't
fulfill that you you know you'll sleep tomorrow, we don't let you
go to sleep today, right? That's how we would read הרי זה
בלא יחל. harei zeh belo yachal. You said it'll be forbidden to
me today if I don't go to sleep tomorrow, and we're saying
we're not going to trust you on tomorrow and therefore
קונם עיני בשינה למחר, Konam einai besheina lemachar, right?
אלא דאמר קונם עיני בשינה למחר, ella de'amar Konam einai besheina lemachar,
oh yeah I'm sorry you're right, you're right, we're starting first that
the תנאי tnai is today, thank you. Okay, קונם עיני בשינה למחר
אם אישן היום. Konam einai besheina lemachar im ishan hayom. If I
sleep today, then then
it'll be forbidden to me tomorrow. And then to say then to
say what do you call it that הרי זה בבל יחל harei
zeh be'val yeichel means that we don't even trust you today to
you know in terms of the תנאי tnai because we don't want
you to be in that position tomorrow where you'll have to keep
your נדר. If that's what it means, המרת כל איסורא מסתייע, hamart
kol issura mistayei, that we allow you to go ahead and to
trigger the תנאי tnai today because we'll trust you tomorrow. Right? So
if it said I'm making a תנאי tnai today and based on
which it'll be אסור assur. to me tomorrow, if that's how we
read the משנה, and הרי זה בבל יחל harei zeh be'val yeichel
means we're not going to let you violate the תנאי tnai today
because we don't want we're not going to trust you to keep
your נדר tomorrow, but we said that's not true. We said we
will trust people in terms of keeping the נדר. So that can't
be the meaning of the משנה, אלא פשיטא ella peshita what we're
finally left with is the debate that we had said, דאמר קונם
עיני בשינה היום אם אישן למחר. de'amar Konam einai besheina hayom im
ishan lemachar. Okay, that actually you said I won't. My eyes are
forbidden today if I sleep tomorrow, and then הרי זה בלא יחל
Harey zeh b'lo yachel means that we don't let you, we don't
let you sleep today because we won't trust you to keep your
תנאי tnai tomorrow.
But that was the debate though.
Right, so that's our קשיא. kashya. We've made the משנה mean one
side of the debate, okay? ואילו לא ניים היום, V'ilu lo nayim
hayom, and if you don't sleep today, כי ניים למחר מאי בלא
יחל דברו איכא? ki nayim l'machar mai b'lo yachel d'varo ika? So
if you're good today, there won't be a בלא יחל b'lo yachel
tomorrow. So if it says there's בלא יחל, b'lo yachel, it means
we won't let you sleep today because we're afraid you won't be
able to be careful tomorrow. אלא לאו בדניים, Ella lav b'dnayim, so
it must mean that there's a concern about you sleeping today because
you won't be able to keep your תנאי tnai tomorrow. אלמא איתא
דניים, Alma ita d'nayim, that it's possible to sleep, ותיובתא דרב יהודה.
u'tyuvta d'Rav Yehuda. Wait a minute. How is it a תיובתא דרב
יהודה? tyuvta d'Rav Yehuda? הרי זה בלא יחל Harey zeh b'lo yachel
should mean that
we—oh now I'm so confused.
Okay, אלא לאו בדניים ella lav b'dnayim means that he actually slept.
So then what does it mean הרי זה בלא יחל, harey zeh
b'lo yachel, wait a minute... אלמא איתא דניים, Alma ita d'nayim, מתניתין
קמשמע לן, matnitin kamashma lan,
הרי זה
בלא יחל,
harey zeh
b'lo
yachel, כלומר הרי זה מותר. klomar harey zeh mutar. Oh my God.
So we just, yeah, the ר"ן Ran asks the question and he
basically says like we're reversing whether הרי זה בלא יחל harey zeh
b'lo yachel means you can't do it because we're afraid you'll be
over in בלא יחל, b'lo yachel, or whether הרי זה בלא יחל
harey zeh b'lo yachel means you can do it and we're not
afraid you'll be over in בלא יחל. b'lo yachel. So I have
no idea but anyway that's how we're reading it, okay? So somehow
we've now read this that the case in the משנה is that
I make—I'm a נדר today if I sleep tomorrow, and הרי זה
בלא יחל harey zeh b'lo yachel means we let you go ahead
and sleep today and we're not afraid that you'll come to transgress
בלא יחל b'lo yachel tomorrow. Don't ask me how come a language
that sounds like it's forbidden all of a sudden now we're assuming
means that we're not afraid that you'll transgress it. So the גמרא
Gemara says anyway somehow that's supposed to be a challenge against רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda who says we won't let you do it tomorrow,
or we won't trust you to do it tomorrow. So the גמרא
Gemara says, no, כי תניא בדניים, ki tanya b'dnayim, now the way
to read the משנה and we'll end with this is not that
you went to sleep and therefore we're going to allow you to
go to sleep today and we're going to trust you to keep
the תנאי tnai tomorrow. It says if you fell asleep today, then
you have to be careful about keeping the תנאי tnai tomorrow, but
it's not a question about whether we're going to allow you to
go to sleep today if you choose to or not. Is everybody
totally confused?
ישר כח, Yasher koach, אמר ליה שמעתא.
Amar
leh shmata. What? Yeah, there you go. Anyway, bottom line is is
that you have an interesting debate, right, if we allow somebody to
do something today that's based on their keeping of the תנאי tnai
tomorrow, we'll retroactively define this as a violation of the תנאי. tnai.
Do you trust somebody to be careful not about the נדר but
about the תנאי? tnai? That's the debate. This case of the משנה
about קונם עיני בשינה, right, the גמרא somehow said, well, it would
be either not true or too obvious if it just meant what
it simply seems to say. So we have to make it say
something more complicated and what we're going to have to make it
say is our scenario where somebody said that they're on a נדר
today based on whether they keep the תנאי tnai tomorrow, okay? And
they wanted to read it, I don't understand how, that הרי זה
בלא יחל harey zeh b'lo yachel means you're allowed to go to
sleep today, we're not afraid you'll transgress בלא יחל, b'lo yachel, and
they wanted to read it that way and the answer was no,
what it means is if you fell asleep today, you'd better be
careful about keeping your תנאי tnai tomorrow, because if you don't keep
your תנאי tnai tomorrow you will have transgressed בלא יחל. b'lo yachel.
But it was hard to see how it fitted into meaning that
case, and even after it meant that case, how it assumed that
it would say it was מותר mutar rather than it saying it
was אסור. The ר\"ן Ran tries to work that through. Okay, but
that's where we'll end for today.
Where's the פסוק pasuk of בלא יחל?
b'lo yachel? By... yeah, exactly. Yeah.